Guide to the Susie Bright papers and On Our Backs records, 1978-2013.
Bright, Susie papers and On Our Backs records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Susie Bright papers and On Our Backs records, 1978-2013.
7788
Bright, Susie,
23.3 cubic feet.
Audio recordings, correspondence, movie film, photographs, publications, research materials, videos.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Records of Bright's work writing and publishing about sexuality, including records of the lesbian sex journal On Our Backs.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Overview: Susie Bright worked for the feminist sex store Good Vibrations, and in 1984 launched the first U.S. lesbian sex magazine, On Our Backs, with photographer Honey Lee Cottrell, publisher Deborah Sundahl, and Nan Kinney. Susie served as the magazine’s editor. An expert on the history of the pornography business and its censorship, she has reviewed erotic movies and written broadly about sexual issues.
Detailed biography: Susannah "Susie" Bright (also known as Susie Sexpert) (born March 25, 1958) is an American feminist, author, journalist, critic, editor, publisher, producer, and performer, often on the subject of sexual politics. Known for her founding role in the magazine On Our Backs, she is also an expert on the history of the pornography business and its censorship and has reviewed erotic movies and written broadly about sexual issues. She is one of the first writer/activists referred to as a sex-positive feminist.
As a teenager, Bright was active in the 1970s in various left-wing progressive causes, in particular the feminist, labor, civil rights, and anti-war movements. She was one of the members of the high school underground newspaper, The Red Tide, and served as Plaintiff suing the Los Angeles Board of Education for the right of minors to distribute their own publications without prior censorship or approval. (Judgement in favor of Plaintiff).
She was a member of the International Socialists from 1974-1976 and worked as a labor and community organizer in Los Angeles, the San Francisco Bay Area, Detroit, MI, and Louisville, Kentucky.
Bright was one of the founding members of Teamsters for a Democratic Union, and wrote under the pseudonym Sue Daniels in both The Red Tide and Workers' Power.
Bright trained with San Francisco Sex Information in 1981. From 1981 to 1986, she worked for and managed Good Vibrations, which Joani Blank had opened in San Francisco in 1977, the second feminist sex toy shop in the country (after Dell Williams’ Eve’s Garden). Bright wrote Good Vibrations’ first mail order catalog, the first sex toy catalog written from a women’s point of a view to a female audience. She founded the Good Vibrations Erotic Video Library, the first feminist curation of erotic films available at the time. During this time, she got involved with a group of artists called "Mainstream Exiles" and co-wrote and starred in two plays: "Girls Gone Bad" and "Knife, Paper, Scissors."
In 1984, she launched the first women-produced magazine on the topic of sex and erotica, On Our Backs, "entertainment for the adventurous lesbian," with photographer Honey Lee Cottrell, publisher Deborah Sundahl, and Nan Kinney. Susie served as the magazine’s editor until 1991. Known as the "Pauline Kael of Porn" Bright wrote feminist reviews of erotic films for Penthouse Forum from 1986–1989. She was the first mainstream journalist who covered the adult industry trade, and Bright was the first female member of the X-Rated Critics Organization in 1986.
She taught the aesthetics and politics of erotic film imagery starting in 1986 at Cal Arts Valencia, and then in the early nineties at the University of California. Her film-reviews of independent and mainstream films and videos are widely published, and her commentary on gay film history are featured in the documentary film The Celluloid Closet.
Bright founded the first women's erotica book-series, Herotica, in 1988 and edited the first three volumes. Susie Sexpert’s Lesbian Sex World, the first collection of her own stories, came out in 1990. She started The Best American Erotica series in 1993, and has edited it annually since then. She published the only portfolio of lesbian erotic photography, Nothing But the Girl, co-edited with Jill Posener, with 30 interviews and photographs from photographers around the world. It won the Firecracker Award and the Lammie Award in 1997. She was voted into the XRCO Hall of Fame, 5th Estate, in 2005.
Bright worked a screenwriter and film consultant in several films: Erotique, The Virgin Machine, The Celluloid Closet, and Bound, and appeared as herself in an episode of the HBO television series, Six Feet Under.
She started a website in March 1997, and began her blog, Susie Bright’s Journal, in 2004.
Since 2000, she has produced and hosted a weekly program In Bed with Susie Bright on Audible, Inc., where she discusses a variety of social, freedom of speech and sex-related topics. Interviews, book and movie reviews are common, as are letters from listeners.
Since 2012, Bright has worked as an editor-at-large executive producer at Audible Inc, and was nominated for a non-fiction Audie Award as executive producer in 2013.
BOOKS
Co-Author with Aretha Bright, Mother/Daughter Sex Advice, Bright Stuff, 2012
Author, The Erotic Screen: Volume 1, Bright Stuff, 2011
Author, Big Sex Little Death, Seal Press, 2011
Author, Love and Lust: A Sex Journal, Chronicle Books, 2010
Author, I Dare You Cards, Chronicle Books, 2010
Editor, Bitten, Chronicle Books, 2009
Editor, X: The Erotic Treasury, Chronicle Books, 2008
Series Editor, Best American Erotica, Simon and Schuster, 1993 - 2008
Editor, Three Kinds of Asking For It, Eric Albert, Greta Christina, and Jill Soloway, edited by Susie Bright, Simon and Schuster, 2005
Editor, Three the Hard Way, by William Harrison, Greg Boyd, and Tsaurah Litzky, edited by Susie Bright, Simon and Schuster, 2004
Mommy's Little Girl: Susie Bright on Sex, Motherhood, Pornography, and Cherry Pie, Thunders Mouth, 2004
How To Write a Dirty Story: Reading, Writing, and Publishing Erotica, Simon and Schuster, 2002
Full Exposure: Opening Up to Sex and Creativity, HarperSanFrancisco, 1999
The Sexual State of the Union, Simon & Schuster, 1997, 1998
Author and Co-Editor, Nothing But the Girl: the Blatant Lesbian Image, Cassell, 1996
SexWise, Cleis Press, 1995
Susie Bright's Sexual Reality: A Virtual Sex Reader, Cleis Press, 1992
Editor, Herotica III, Penguin USA, 1994
Editor, Herotica II, Penguin USA, 1992
Susie Sexpert's Lesbian Sex World, Cleis Press, 1990
Editor, Herotica, Down There Press, 1988
BLOG
Susie Bright's Journal, 2004 - present
AUDIO
Editor-at-Large and Executive Producer, Audible, Inc., 2011 - present
Executive Producer and Host, In Bed with Susie Bright, on Audible.com, 2000 - present
Author and Director, Full Exposure, Produced by HarperAudio, 1999
Contributing Author and Perfomer, Food, Sex and Relationships, with Harriet Lerner and Mollie Katzen, produced by Worley Management and Sounds True, 1997
Contributing Author and Perfomer, Cyborgasm, produced by Lisa Palac and Ron Gommpertz, Heydey/Time Warner, 1994.
Contributing Author and Perfomer, The Edge of the Bed, produced by Lisa Palac, Heydey/Time Warner,1995.
Editor and Performer, Herotica, produced by Passion Press, 1995
Editor, Herotica 2, produced by Passion Press, 1995
Editor, Herotica 3, produced by Passion Press, 1997
TELEVISION, VIDEO, AND FILM
Special Feature Interview, Reissue of "Belle de Jour", (directed by Luis Buñuel) produced by Issa Massu, Criterion Collection, 2011
Featured Guest, 1969, produced by Rob Epstein, broadcast on The History Channel, 2009
Featured Guest, Six Feet Under, produced by HBO, broadcast on HBO, 2006
Featured Guest, Retrosexual: The 80s, produced by VH1, 2004
Featured Guest, Sex in the 20th Century, narrated by Peter Coyote, produced by MPH Entertainment, broadcast on History Channel, April 2001
Featured Guest, A Return to Modesty, produced by Lifetime Television, August 1999
Documentary feature, Susie Bright, Sex Pest, produced by Mike Bluett, directed by Cheryl Farthing, for Channel 4, London, England, November 1998
Script Consultant, Choreographer, and Featured Cameo, Bound, produced by Dino DeLaurentis, and directed by Larry and Andy Wachowski, 1996.
Co-star, The Celluloid Closet, produced by Telling Pictures and directed by Rob Epstein and Jeffrey Friedman, 1995.
Screenwriter, Let's Talk About Sex, produced by Brandon Chase, and directed by Lizzie Borden, 1994
Documentary Feature, Reel Sex #8, HBO, Produced by Patty Kaplan, March 1994
Producer and Narrator, All-Girl Action, 1990
Producer and Narrator, How To Read a Dirty Movie, 1990.
Co-star, The Virgin Machine, directed by Monica Treut, W. Germany/US, 1988
PERIODICALS & WEB
Editor, Susie Bright's Journal, 2004 - present
Golden Dukes Annual Judge, Talking Points Memo, 2007 - present
Syndicated Columnist, Jezebel, 2009
Syndicated Columnist, Alternet, 2007
Syndicated Columnist, Huffington Post, 2006
Columnist, CRAFT, 2006-2009
Columnist, Bust, 2002-2005
Columnist, Playboy, 1999-2000
Columnist, Libida, 2000-2001
Contributing Editor, Salon, 1997-2000
Contributing Editor, San Francisco Review of Books, 1992-1994
Editor, On Our Backs, 1984-1991
Contributing Editor, Penthouse Forum, 1987-1989
Frequent Contributor: Esquire, New York Times, Elle, Dwell, Playboy, MS., The Realist, UTNE Reader, San Francisco Chronicle, San Jose Mercury News, Hungry Minds Review, Village Voice, & The Stranger.
LEGAL
Co-Plaintiff, ACLU v. Gonzales (C.O.P.A. case), Supreme Court, 2003-2006. Judgement in favor of Plaintiff.
Consultant, Little Sisters Book and Art Emporium v. Commissioner of Customs and Revenue and Minister of National Revenue - S.C.B.C. Action No. L020443, Queens Court, Canada, 2003-2004. Judgement in favor of Plaintiff.
Plaintiff, Bright v. Los Angeles Unified Sch. Dist., 18 Cal.3d 450, 1974-1976. Judgement in favor of Plaintiff.
PERFORMANCE/CLASSES/PUBLIC LECTURES
Sexual State of the Union Address:
92nd Street Y, New York
Alfred U., New York
Antioch University, Ohio
University of California at Berkeley
University of Colorado, Boulder
Bryn Mawr College
Carnegie Mellon
California State University at Chico
Cornell University
Florida State University
Gay and Lesbian Community Center, New York
Harvey Milk Democratic Club, San Francisco
Haverford College, Philadelphia
Hobart and William Smith Colleges
Humboldt State Univesity
Hunter College, NYC
University of Indiana, Bloomington
University of Wisconsin at Madison
McGill University
University of Michigan at Ann Arbor
MIT
Murfreesboro State University, TN
Ohio State
University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
Northwestern University
University of Pennsylvania
Smith College
Society for the Scientific Study of Sex
Solo Mio Performance Festival, Boston
University of Toronto
Tucson Public Library
Tulane University
Vassar College
Washington State University, Bellingham
Wayne State University
Wellesley College, Massachusetts
Wesleyan Univerisity
Williams College
Sex Education in the Doctor's Office:
University of California, San Francisco
University of California, Berkeley
The Politics of Sexual Representation:
University of California at Santa Cruz
The Case of Pornography, Keynote speaker
UCSB conference on Pornography and Censorship, Santa Barbara
Reading, Writing and Rethinking Erotica:
Esalen Institute
Omega Institute
New College of California
How To Read a Dirty Movie, film show and lecture:
HBO Broadcast
Virginia Tech
Hamburg Gay Film Festival
Berlin Gay Film Festival
Castro Theater, San Francisco
University of California at Santa Cruz
Pacific Film Archive, University of California at Berkeley
Nuart Theater, Los Angeles
Massachusetts Institute of Technology
Collective for Living Cinema
Dobie Theater, Austin
Roxie Theater, San Francisco
San Francisco State University
Stanford University
Cal Arts Valencia
The Victoria Theater
All Girl Action, The History of Lesbian Eroticism in Hollywood, film show & lecture:
Castro Theater, San Francisco
University of Washington, Seattle
British Film Institute
Amsterdam Gay & Lesbian Film Festival, Holland
Nuart Theater, Los Angeles
University of Minnesota, Minneapolis
Hallwalls, Buffalo
Chatham College, Pittsburgh
Gay Film Festival, Music Box Theater, Chicago
Lesbian and Gay Film Festival, Castro Theater, San Francisco
Sex In Public: Erotic Expression, Censorship, and Sexual Repression, a lecture:
American Library Association, San Francisco
Modern Language Association, San Francisco
University of Indiana, Bloomington
Slim's Spoken Word Series, San Francisco
Yale University
University of Arkansas
Cornell University
Wesleyan University
Amherst College,
Harvard University
Brown University
State University of New York, Binghamton
Hunter College, New York
Sex Educators and Erotica, a lecture:
Society for the Scientific Study of Sex
Institute for the Study of Human Sexuality
Keynote Speaker, Multi-Topic:
BlogHer
San Francisco Public Library
Crown Gallery
University of Kansas at Lawrence
Sacred Elixirs
University of Ohio at Columbus
L.A. Times Book Festival
Romantic Times
Seattle Public Library
AWARDS & BESTSELLERS
Gail Rich Award, Santa Cruz, 2002
Lambda Literary Award, Best Art Book of the Year, 1997, for Nothing But the Girl
Firecracker Award, Best Art Book of the Year, 1997, for Nothing But the Girl
Full Exposure, National Bestseller
Best American Erotica, National Bestseller
Sexual State of the Union, National Bestseller
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records of Bright's work writing and publishing about sexuality, including the lesbian sex journal On Our Backs, that document American sexual politics since 1978 and show the development of her own activism and thinking about sexual liberation. Her collection contains the history of On Our Backs - magazine issues, production documents, and media and reader responses that document the feminist sex wars and censorship battles that defined lesbian publishing in the 1980s and 1990s. Also included are videos and documents used by Bright in lectures and teaching about censorship and pornography controversies, Bright's collection of pornographic films, articles and photographs that document Bright's career, and works by various artists, writers and activists that contextualize Bright's work within the arena of sexual liberation and feminism. The collection also includes material from Bright's activism during her high school career at University High School and early college career in California. Documents detail Bright's work in various organizations,the International Socialists, Teamsters for a Democratic Union, and the Red Tide, that each contributed to the feminist, labor, civil rights, and anti-war movements. Material also covers Bright's experience as a plaintiff suing the Los Angeles Board of Education when University High School administration attempted to prevent the distribution of the Red Tide underground newspaper. Scripts and drafts of Bright's first plays "Girls Gone Bad" and "Knife, Paper, Scissors." Readers used by Bright when teaching her university courses on the subjects of the politics of sexuality and pornographic films. Pieces written by Bright for various publications, whether as a guest writer or as a regular columnist. Also a collection of the media attention to Bright's publications,including the negative and positive responses to her controversial contribution to the Sexual Revolution and Feminist Porn Wars. Submissions for Counter Visions photography project. Issues of On Our Backs, various files pertaining to the business of producing OOB, as well as the Stormy Leather catalog, the OOB 1989 Lesbian Sex Calendar and Fatale Video; and articles that account for the critical and popular reception of OOB as well as OOB's contribution to the Sexual Revolution and Feminist Porn Wars. Personal photographs, letters, papers and works of and by the OOB staff document the lives of the women behind the magazine and their experience working for OOB and attending OOB related events. Also included is a collection of slides from pornographic films. Bright's collection of prints, drawings and collages,notably drawings by Noreen Scully and works by Honey Lee Cottrell; posters of various films and performances; and images from a variety of photographers. Costumes worn by Debi Sundahl as Fanny Fatale for the performance of BurLEZk, a lesbian striptease performance, at the Mitchell Bros O'Farrell Theater. Bright's collection of pornographic videos spanning 1930-2007 as well as recordings of Bright's news appearances, lectures, award shows and interviews. Interviews with Bright. Publications containing articles by Susie Bright or about Susie Bright and various publications collected by Bright.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bright, Susie, 1958-; Cottrell, Honey Lee.; Kinney, Nan.; Sundahl, Deborah.
Subjects:
Bright, Susie, 1958-; Feminism.; Sex oriented businesses.; Erotica.; Pornographic films.; Pornography.; Sex Instruction.; Women -- Sexual behavior.; Women-owned business enterprises.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Box 16 Folders 22-24, Erotic Film and Video Survey questionnaires, are restricted to permission of the Human Sexuality Curator.
Box 25 is not for patron use.
NOTES
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Early Material
Box 20
Series II. Teaching
Box 16
Series III. Writing
Boxes 16-19
Miscellaneous writings
Best American Erotica
Media Books
Salon Magazine: Sexpert Opinion by Susie Bright
Series IV. Counter Visions
Boxes 13, 14
Series V. On Our Backs
Boxes 13, 14, 21, 23, 24, 25
On Our Backs Issues
Administrative Files
On Our Backs Media
On Our Backs Photos and Miscellaneous
Series VI. Oversize Items
Boxes 14, 22, map case
Artwork
Posters
Large Photographs
Series VII. Costumes of Debi Sundahl
Box 15
Series VIII. Videos
Boxes 1-11
Series IX. Audio Recordings
Box 12
Series X. Periodicals
Boxes 14, 21
Susie Bright Related Periodicals
Miscellaneous Periodicals
Series XI. Separated Material
Cataloged individually
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Early Material
  Material from Bright’s activism during her high school career at University High School and early college career in California. Documents detail Bright’s work in various organizations, the International Socialists, Teamsters for a Democratic Union, and the Red Tide, that each contributed to the feminist, labor, civil rights, and anti-war movements. Material also covers Bright’s experience as a plaintiff suing the Los Angeles Board of Education when University High School administration attempted to prevent the distribution of the Red Tide underground newspaper. This series also includes scripts and drafts of Bright’s first plays “Girls Gone Bad” and “Knife, Paper, Scissors.”
  - Girls Gone Bad (Box 20, Folder 1)
    Drafts, news articles, illustrations, notes, brainstorming
  - GMHS certificate for Sextoys booth (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Knife, Paper, Scissors (Box 20, Folder 3)
    Script, reviews, photographs, notes
  - Red Tide (Uni High LA), 1974 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    Bulletins, flyers, articles, petitions
  - Bright vs. Board of Ed (Red Tide censorship battle), 1975 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Red Tide Study Group, LA, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - Red Tide LA Police Campaign, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1977-79 Post International Socialists, 1977-1979 (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - Santa Cruz Women Take Back the Night, 1980 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    Flyers, journal entries, meeting notes, articles, programs
  - FPS-A Magazine of Young People's Liberation, March 1975 (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - International Socialists Folk Song Book (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - International Socialists Faction Fight, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - Red Tide Detroit (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - Red Tide security (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - Red Tide/CCSC Bay Area notes (Box 20, Folder 15)
  - Red Tide internal documents, 1975-1977 (Box 20, Folder 16)
  - Detroit Red Tide/International Socialists internal documents (Box 20, Folder 17)
  - Detroit Red Tide public documents-flyers, events (Box 20, Folder 18)
  - Red Tide LA (Box 20, Folder 19)
  - Red Tide articles by Bright, drafts (Box 20, Folder 20)
  - Response to Anita Bryant's Save Our Children campaign (Box 20, Folder 21)
  - International Socialists Louisville Branch (Box 20, Folder 22)
  - Dead Tide (Box 20, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 24)
  - International Socialists Faction Fight, 1977 (Box 20, Folder 25)
  - Teamsters for a Democratic Union/UPSurge, 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 26)
  - Susie Bright's print work with International Socialists (Box 20, Folder 27)
- Series II. Teaching
  Readers used by Bright when teaching her university courses on the subjects of the politics of sexuality and pornographic films.
  - Lesbian Gay Social Worlds, Winter 1999 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Course Reader
  - Lesbian Gay Social Worlds, Winter 1999 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    Susie's Copy
  - The Best of the Politics of Sexual Representation, Winter 1997 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Community Studies 112, BRT 133
  - Politics of Sexual Representation Reader, Winter 1997 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Instructor Copy
  - Politics of Sexual Representation Reader, Winter 1997 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    Loose Leaf Copy
  - Politics of Sexual Representation Reader, Winter 1997 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Bound Copy
  - Politics of Sexuality, Spring 1981 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    Community Studies 42A. Nancy Shaw Faculty Sponsor
  - Politics of Sexualiy; A Student-Directed-Seminar, Spring 1981/April 1982 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    Community Studies. Nancy Shaw Faculty Sponsor
  - Special Topics in Film Genre: Pornographic Film, Summer 1996 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    FS 150PG, Constance Penley
  - Film Studies 112: Pornography (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Crosslisted: Women's Studies 174 A/ Anteater Publishing, Williams
  - BRT 1001 The Film Editor (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - BRT 1002 On Set with Clay McCord (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - BRT 1003 Contemporary Erotic Cinema (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - BRT 1004 Introduction to X rated films (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - BRT 1005 Pink Ladies Social Club, March 1989 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - BRT 1006 Pink Ladies Social Club, August 1989 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - BRT 1008 Homegrown Video, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 17)
- Series III. Writings
  Pieces written by Bright for various publications, whether as a guest writer or as a regular columnist. Bright wrote for Salon Magazine, an online magazine on contemporary culture, under her column “Sexpert Opinion” from 1997 to 1999. From 1986-1989, she contributed erotic film reviews regularly to Penthouse Forum, a journal containing articles on controversial and pornographic topics. Also included in this series is a collection of the media attention to Bright’s publications—including the negative and positive responses to her controversial contribution to the Sexual Revolution and Feminist Porn Wars.
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - Penthouse Forum Articles, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 18)
      Articles by Susie for the column the Erotic Screen, The Cream of Adult Videos, Adult Video Advisor
    - Penthouse Forum Articles, 1987-1989 (Box 16, Folder 19)
      Originals from the magazine and additional copies. Mostly for the column the Erotic Screen, The Cream of Adult Videos
      - "Two Days on a Porn Set" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Adult Videos for Couples" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "The Awful Truth" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Desperately Seeking Erotica" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Double Whammy" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Fanny Get Your Gun"
      - "Father Knows Best" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "A Fruit of Another Color" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Gay and Biosexual Video" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "I Am Curious (Butterball)" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "John Holmes" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Kittens do Become Cats" (Box 16, Folder 19)
      - "Lesbian Lowdown" (Box 16, Folder 19)